Inventory of the Afghan partisan serials collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Mujaheddin-era Publications, 1984-2001
  - شهادت (Shahadat, Martyrdom), حمل 1371 (Hamal) 2 - عقرب 1371 (Aqrab) 7, (1992 March 22 - 1992 October 29)
    No. 1 through no. 99 (single year). 157 issues (numbering irregular) of the Pushto-Dari daily newspaper, which at the time served as the official organ of Gulbuddin Hekmatyar's faction of the Mujaheddin, covering a pivotal year in the post-Soviet power struggle from the time of Najibullah's fall through the transitional government of Sibghatullah Mojaddedi, with articles accusing Ahmad Shah Masood of collaboration with the Russians and allied Afghan groups, illustrated throughout with reproductions of photographs and satirical cartoons. Published in Peshawar, Pakistan (Urgan-i-Markazi, Hezb-e Islami Afghanistan) from 1992-1993 (1371).
  - سیمای وحدت (Sima-ye Wahdat, Portrait of Unity), حوت 1375 (Hut) 6 - اسد 1377 (Asad) 8, (1997 February 24 - 1998 July 30)
    Year 1, no. 2 through Year 2, no. 58 (near complete, lacking first issue). 57 issues (with no. 48 provided in duplicate), circa 4-6 pages each, of Mohammad Akbari's Pasdaran faction Hizb-e Wahdat Dari-language newspaper, largely addressing an Hazara audience, including regular features on women's rights under the rule of Islam. Published in Peshawar, Pakistan (Urgan-i Nasharati Hezb-i Wahdat lslami Afghanistan - Pakistan Branch) from 1997-1998 (1375-1377).
    This serial is considerably more moderate than the Taliban hard-line position, although Akbari joined the Taliban in September 1998 following conflicts with rival Hazara leader Abdul Ali Mazari.
  - مستقبال (Mustaqbal, Future), جوزا 1378 (Jausa) 10 - جدی 1380 (Jadi) 10, (1999 May 31 - 2001 December 31)
    Year 1, no. 1 through Year 3, nos. 6-7 (all published). 19 issues, circa 65-125 pages each, comprising a complete run of Jamiat-i Islami's social, cultural, and political magazine discussing the future of Afghanistan, published in Dari and Pushto from exile in Peshawar by Nasir Ahmad Nawidi and Mohammad Aajan Haqpal under the supervision of Sifatullah Qanet during the time of the Taliban takeover, presenting a more moderate vision of Islamic governance, including articles on the unity of science and religion, profiles of historical figures, and anti-PDPA texts, illustrated throughout with reproductions of contemporary and historical photographs. Published in Peshawar, Pakistan from 1999-2001 (1378-1380).
    This serial provides a look at the political and cultural vision of Ahmad Shah Masood's Jamiat-i lslami party in the last years of his life, up until his murder by the Taliban, the events of 9/11, and subsequent U.S. invasion.
- Taliban-era Publications, 1995-2001
  Arising in response to the brutality and lawlessness of the Afghan civil war, the Taliban consolidated forces under the leadership of Mullah Omar in Kandahar circa 1994. Extolling strict adherence to the Koran as the key to social order, the group successfully fought the remaining Mujaheddin factions for control of the country in 1996. Until they were toppled by American forces in December 2001, the Taliban regularly issued newspapers and magazines that chronicled their military and political ascent, promoted Islamic virtue, and reinforced Sharia law.
  - طلوع افغان (Tolu’-e Afghan, Dawn of Afghanistan), حمل 1374 (Hamal) 1 - میزان 1380 (Mizan) 14, (1995 March 21 - 2001 October 6)
    Year 1374, no. 1 (also called issue 10) through year 1380, no. 390 (near complete run of issues published under the Taliban, lacking approximately 23 numbers). [Alternate title: Tolo-e-Afghan.] Approximately 415 issues, circa 4 pages each, of the semi-weekly (note: while the subtitle describes it as a daily, publication dates reflect a less frequent delivery schedule; numbering erratic) Pushto and Dari newspaper, edited by Maulavi Ahmad Jan Ahmadi and published by the Taliban’s Ministry of Information and Culture in Khandahar, largely broadcasting the group's Islamist principles, with statements attributed to Mullah Omar concerning the role of women in Islamic societies, governance by Islamic teachers and intellectuals, warnings to rival warlords and Islamist groups, etc., alongside some coverage of national and international affairs, as well as poetry and other cultural writings. Chiefly text. Published in Kandahar, Afghanistan (Da Etla'ato Aw Kultur Riyasat) from 1995-2001 (1374-1380).
    The serial presents the Taliban's political and social self-presentation from the time of their military ascendance through the post-9/11 period. Includes articles about the Clinton-era attacks on Tora Bora and the Taliban's protection of Osama Bin Laden.
  - شریعت (Shari'at, Sharia), Kandahar, Afghanistan, قوس 1374 (Qaus) 27 - قوس 1379 (Qaus) 29, (1995 December 18 - 2000 December 19)
    Year 1, no. 1 through Year 5, no. 93 (inconsistently numbered, some issues bound out of sequence). [Alternate title in English from year two: Shariat Weekly.] 384 issues, comprising a near complete collection (lacking only year 1, no. 3) of the official weekly (later semi-weekly) newspaper of the Taliban movement, largely in Pushto with some Dari, edited by Maulavi Ahmad Jan Ahmadi, Mullah Asadullah Hanifi, Maulavi Abdul Rahman Ahmad Hotaki, and others, covering Afghan and Islamic history and governance, Afghan and international news, and official decrees, alongside extensive anti-Rabbani, anti-communist, and anti-Western writings, sparsely illustrated in accordance with strict Sharia law prohibiting graven images. Occasional special issues in color ink. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan and Peshawar, Pakistan (Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan) from 1995-2000 (1374-1379).
    Established prior to the group’s control of the Afghan government under Mullah Omar (who was declared Amir-ul-Mumineen, or Supreme Caliph of Islam, in April 1996), Shari'at charts the rise of the Taliban from its earliest influence through the apex of its rule. Specific topics include the corruption of the Rabbani government, reports linking Iran with Ahmad Shah Masood and the Northern Alliance, condemnations of Israel, Osama Bin Laden's alliance with the Taliban and international efforts to prosecute him, limits to the opium trade, India and Pakistan, Chechnaya, and the Clinton sex scandal.
  - خلافت (Khilafat, Caliphate), Kabul, Afghanistan, جوزا 1375 (Jauza) 11 - دلو 1379 (Asad) 12, (1996 May 31 - 2001 January 31)
    Year 1, no. 1 through Year 5, no. 21 (all published). 26 issues in 18 fascicules, circa 64-86 pages each, comprising what an expert source says is a complete run of the monthly Dari-Pushto magazine of the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan under the Taliban, edited by Maulavi Faqir Mohammad Khanjari (founded by Tarik Islami Taliban Afghanistan under the supervision of Shuray-e Farhangi), including direct statements by Mullah Omar, Koranic citations and teachings, articles on the proper role of women in an Islamic society, and the differentiation of jihad terrorism. Chiefly text. Published in Kandahar, Afghanistan (Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan-Taliban) from 1996-2001 (1375-1380).
    The articles included are reflective of the hard-line Kandahar branch of the Taliban, where Mullah Omar resided during his governance of Afghanistan.
  - اتفاق اسلام (Ittifaq-e Islam, Union of Islam), ثور 1375 (Saur) 23 - 19 سنبله 1380 (Sonbola) 19, (1996 May 12 - 2001 September 10)
    Collation of erratically numbered issues (scattered numbers, largely incomplete). Approximately 86 issues, circa 4 pages each, of the major Dari and Pushto-language daily newspaper of Herat, edited by Ghulam Hazrat "Jaheed" and Mohammad Qazi Zada and authorized by the Taliban's Ministry of Information and Culture, showing some nuances and differences with the more hard-line Taliban newspapers of Kabul from the same period, but also emphasizing the rule of Islamic law and the military and civil accomplishments of the Taliban. Chiefly text, illustrated with sparse graphic flourishes and images of mosques. Published in Herat, Afghanistan (Dawlati Matbaah-Riyasat-e Etla'at Wa Kultur, Herat) from 1996-2001 (1375-1380).
  - هيواد (Hewad, Homeland), میزان 1375 (Mizan) 21 - میزان 1380 (Mizan) 12, (1996 October 12 - 2001 October 4)
    Issues incomplete. [Alternate English title: Hewad Daily.] 262 issues, circa 4-8 pages each, of the semi-weekly Taliban newspaper published in Pushto (with some Dari) by the Ministry of Defense under the editorship of Abdul Hanan "Himmat," Abdul Hadi "Rawan," Ilhaj Mullah Asadullah "Hanifi," and Mullah Mohammad lbrahim "Nabil" during the occupation of Kabul, including direct statements from Taliban commanders to the people of Afghanistan explaining the group's policies and agendas, coverage of its struggle against the Northern Alliance, statements and decrees by Amir-ul-Mumineen Mullah Muhammad Omar Mujahid (Mullah Omar), as well as poetry, articles on Islamic faith, and some local and international news. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan (De Urdu de Matbe'a Chaap) from 1996-2001 (1375-1380).
    The collection of issues documents the Taliban's self-presentation of its military achievements and philosophy of Islamic jihad. Also contains news coverage of the events of September 11, 2001 from the Taliban point of view.
  - انیس (Anis, Companion), میزان 1375 (Mizan) 26 - میزان 1380 (Mizan) 14, (1996 October 17 - 2001 October 6)
    No. 18754 through no. 19345 (incomplete). [Alternate English title: Anis Daily Newspaper.] Approximately 600 issues (lacking circa 180 issues from the stated date range; numbering erratic) of the Dari and Pushto-language daily newspaper published by the Afghan Ministry of lnformation and Culture (est. 1927), comprising an incomplete though substantial run covering the five years of Taliban governance in Afghanistan, from the group's capture of Kabul in 1996 through the U.S. bombardment and invasion in 2001, offering an officially sanctioned view of daily life, culture, politics, current events, international affairs, and religious propriety in the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan under the leadership of Mullah Omar. Some issues illustrated with bold graphic art showing the military prowess of the Taliban as a warning to foreign invaders. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan (Dawlati Matbaah) from 1996-2001 (1375-1380).
    Articles include direct statements from the Taliban leadership and former Mujaheddin commanders from before and after the events of September 11, 2001, as well as a defiant statement from Osama Bin Laden concerning the attacks.
  - سنگر (Sangar, Trench), جدی 1375 (Jadi) 3 - دلو 1377 (Dalw) 26, (1996 December 23 - 1999 February 15)
    Vol. 1, no. 1 through no. 60 (partial year, lacking 6 nos.: 6, 9, 14, 17, 28, 32; inconsistently numbered). 54 issues, circa 4 pages each, of the militant newspaper published in Dari and Pushto by the Defense Ministry of the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan under the Taliban (edited by Maulavi Hamdullah Hamid) in support of the policies of Mullah Omar, covering the war efforts against the Northern Alliance and other topics related to religion and warfare. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan (Nasharia-i Wizarat Defa-i Mili Emarat Islami Afghanistan) from 1996-1997 (1375-1377).
    This series was launched immediately after the Taliban takeover of Kabul and seemingly discontinued shortly thereafter.
  - The Islamic Emirate, ربيع الثاني 1421 (Rabi' al-thani) 29 - صفر 1422 (Safar) 7, (2000 July 31 - 2001 April 30)
    No. 1 through no. 7 (all published). Seven issues, circa 33-45 pages each, comprising a complete run of the official English-language publication of the lslamic Emirate of Afghanistan under Amir-ul-Mumineen Mullah Muhammad Omar Mujahid (Mullah Omar), edited by Maulavi Ahmad Jan Ahmadi, including translations of decrees and fatwas, broad and specific refutations of Western media reports concerning the Taliban, statements concerning the origins and objectives of the Islamic Emirate, discussions of the Ministry for the Promotion of Virtue and Prevention of Vice, interviews with Jalaluddin Haqqani and Osama Bin Laden, and coverage of the Taliban's efforts to stop the trade of narcotics in Afghanistan, etc., chiefly text. Published in Kandahar, Afghanistan (Information Centre of the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan) from 2000-2001.
    As the official English-language organ of the Taliban, it reflects the hard-line anti-Western views of its publishers in the months directly prior to the events of September 11, 2001 and the American invasion.
- Karzai-era Publications, 2002-2009
  After the events of September 11, 2001, American-led coalition forces invaded Afghanistan and deposed the Taliban, making way for the presidency of Hamid Karzai. In the decade since his initial appointment, the government has progressively restored civil rights that were restricted under the Taliban, including freedom of the press. In addition to pro-government newspapers and magazines, a variety of critical voices can be found among the emerging print media outlets of the Karzai era.
  - پلوشه (Palwashah, Clarity), عقرب 1381 (Aqrab) 20 - حوت 1385 (Hut) 20, (November 11, 2002-March 11, 2007)
    Vol. 3, no. 1 through Vol. 3, year 4, no. 79 (complete run of stated date range; numbering erratic). 75 issues of the semi-monthly Pashtun nationalist magazine published in Dari and Pushto under the editorship of Dr. Akmal Ghilgi Skwandi, including articles on the social and political situation in Afghanistan during the early Karzai period, moderately Islamist and pro-Sardar Daoud Khan in tendency, but anti-communist. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan (Matba'a Ghazali) from 2002-2007 (1381-1385).
  - ویسا (Weesa, Trust), ثور 1385 (Saur) 5 - حمل 1389 (Hamal) 30, (2006 April 25 - 2010 April 19)
    Year 1, no. 1 through Year 4, no. 1186 (complete head of series through fourth year of publication). [Alternate title in Library of Congress listings: Visa.] Approximately 1180 issues, circa 4 pages each, comprising an unbroken head-of-series run (slight numbering irregularities and minor date gaps throughout, which an expert source says is consistent with the serial's publishing history) of one of the major Karzai-era newspapers, published daily (except Thursdays and Fridays) in Dari and Pushto under the pro-coalition editorship of Mohib Bizar, including reports on the armed struggle against the Taliban (as well as early indications of peace negotiations), national and international politics and current affairs, entertainment, sports, development, and foreign aid. Published in Kabul, Afghanistan (Mohib Bizar) from 2006-2010 (1385-1389).
    Later issues, as security in Kabul deteriorated, show public service announcements for the prevention of suicide attacks, as well as a proliferation of advertisements for internet and cell phone companies.
  - اسلام غږ (Islam Ghagh, Voice of Islam), سرطان 1387 (Saratan) 10 - سرطان 1388 (Saratan) 29, (2008 June 30 - 2009 July 20)
    No. 1 through no. 4 (all published). [Alternate English title: Voice of Islam Monthly Publication.] Four issues, circa 48 pages each, comprising a complete run of the political, cultural, and social monthly magazine published mainly in Pushto (and some Dari) by Mishr Maulavi Sayeb Saeedullah Saeed under the editorship of Habib Shah Ansari and Sada Haider Kheil, with articles concerning the unchanging nature of Islam even under chaotic political and national events, the difficulties of life in Kabul under the Russians and Americans, statements against the Taliban massacres and suicide attacks, calls to end ethnic divisions and unite the nation, condemnations of civilian casualties by occupation forces, etc., illustrated throughout with reproductions of photographs and desktop publishing clipart. Published in Kabul and Khost, Afghanistan (De Mujahideno Mili Yawali lslami Tahrik Mishr, Maulavi Saeedullah Saeed) from 2008-2009 (1387-1388).
    This serial provides a perspective from Khost province on topics of national and international concern, as well as household matters, from the evils of drugs and alcohol to childhood education, and the importance of hijab for Afghan women.
- Other Materials, 1991, 2011
  - تقویم (Taqvim, Calendar), Kabul, Afghanistan, in Dari, number of issues: 1, 1991
  - سراج التواریخ (Siraj al-Tavarikh, Lamp of Chronicles: The History of Afghanistan), کابل :‏ ‏متبعه حروفى دار السلطنه،, Kabul, Afghanistan, in Dari and Pushto, number of issues: 1, 2011